Okay.
In this lecture, we're going to cover
what, cloud load balancers are.
All the cloud service providers
have both built in services
and allow you to run your own cloud,
or load balancer after.
No better word.
The reason we have them,
the most important reason is availability.
If I have a no go down, I can easily
reconnect through a load balancer.
Also scalability, performance.
And in addition, a little bit of security,
which we'll talk about
some different security aspects of this
as well.
Cloud service providers typically provide
two types of load balancers
in two broad categories.
Both layer four,
which is the transport layer,
in the network, and then also layer seven,
which is application based.
And we're going to talk a little bit
about what
the differences are between those two.
But the main functionality underneath
the covers is the same.
I have a client come in and
I need to redirect that client request
to somewhere.
Right.
And that's
what a load balancer really helps you do.
So why high availability.
So first and foremost
what I hate that term first and foremost.
But I just said it there. You go.
High availability.
So if I have services on the back end
that are failing or they're failing
health checks or whatever,
I can redirect traffic to,
replica of that instance of that service.
So without the client even knowing or
caring, it doesn't it doesn't really know.
So this provides me the ability
to do really high availability,
especially even if I have to, have,
a federation of load balancers
where they're across
multiple clouds or across
multiple regions of a certain cloud.
I can set that up as well.
So I have a region goes down.
I'm still protected.
The other one is scalability.
And I've run into this, issue myself.
When I was a CIO, we launched
a brand new, externally facing,
tool, for our customers.
And we did not have the scalability built
in, and we were overwhelmed
within minutes of launching it.
Putting a load balancer
on the front end of that
would have been the right thing to do.
We did not.
And that was a huge mistake
that we, had in the architecture,
you know, 30 years ago.
I can't believe it's been that long.
Maybe not 30, 20, 20 years ago.
So scalability really important.
And one of the benefits that you get
from a load balancer, I can auto scale
and spin up multiple new, instances
of my back in services as I need to.
I can also handle some of the performance
and latency latency issues by being smart
about where my load balancer
is spinning up instances.
If they're on separate networks,
is that going to slow me down?
Do I want them all on the same network?
There's lots of different things
that you can play around
with as far as a load balancer goes.
And then the last one,
and probably one of the most important
aspects of this is security.
I can centralize my token sharing, my SSL
and TLS, terminations
can happen at a load balancer.
I can log everything coming into my system
so it gives a single choke point.
For security, I can handle,
DDoS attacks and,
all those sorts of things right there.
At one point,
instead of it overwhelming all my backend
and causing chaos in the backend.
So load balancers, good thing. Right?
Because they give me that isolation.
They also give me the ability
to auto scale and, and,
give me high availability
and also a security, as we mentioned.
All right.
There's two different types
that we have here.
The first type, being an L4 layer
for on the network,
which talks about the TCP, UDP layer.
So these load balancers
handle network traffic.
They're not they don't know anything
about the application.
They're just saying
all right, I'm going to forward
this to this other
service that's over here.
I'm just forwarding packets.
That's all.
That's all I worry about. Right.
And it's highly effective
for a lot of types of applications
where I don't need to know
what's going on.
The application
layer, super highly parallelized,
type of applications work
well with layer four.
Layer seven is, is a little bit,
more this I,
I can share sessions across
as I need to across different, instances
of the same application.
This is more,
path based and host type based,
routing or if that's right, for,
for your load balancing.
So for this, there is some knowledge
in the load balancer about the endpoints
and where they're all at,
where on the layer four.
It's just
I have got replicas of the same, stack
and I'm just pumping stuff through.
So you have to understand, the differences
between the two.
And then that's a great exercise
to figure out.
Well, which one's better
for what types of applications.
So go out and research that some more.
And you'll find that,
one is not best for all.
And that's something
that you can take advantage of.
All right.
Layer for transport layer.
Let's give, some, deep examples here.
As I mentioned
before, operates on the TCP, UDP.
It uses IP addresses and ports for its,
configuration, simple,
very high performance forwarding.
Like I said, no visibility into into the,
RESTful,
RESTful endpoint paths or the headers.
And it's passed through
as far as, TLS goes,
but it does support TCP, UDP and SSL
for for security examples.
AWS network load balancer.
Does this cloud,
Google Cloud, does this Azure load
balancer, all that that all at that level.
Very easy.
To establish because I don't need to know
about the application stack,
but it also means
I don't know about the application stack.
So I can't have more intelligent
type of load balancing
okay.
Layer seven application, level of the IP
stack operates on Https
and gRPC, MCP,
any any of those higher up, application
protocols.
It understands
the request fields coming in.
I can put in advanced routing
based off of the URL path, host header
or even http t p methods in cookies
and things like that.
So I have a lot more control
over the scheduling
and what I want to do, with,
that request that comes
in, I can break it down in
and serve it on the back
end in a lot of different ways.
It does support SSL and TLS termination.
I can do request rewriting.
And also it also supports WebSocket,
which is, very important
if you want a highly interactive,
client and back end server, applications
example on this is AWS
has an application load balancer
and API gateway fits well with this.
Google Cloud has a Http load balancer,
an Azure Application gateway.
So they put in their
the names application.
It should be recognizable for you
remember layer seven load balancers.
I can do a lot more
with their little bit slower.
Not much.
Layer seven less configure,
less configure ability.
Easy to deploy.
Lightning fast.
Okay.
There are different, deployment models.
Now think of a load balancer as I can
run it as an external
or public load balancer,
where clients are connecting into my,
cluster of microservices that are running.
So that gives me that choke point
on the outside.
But internally inside my cluster in this,
micro segmented, network,
I can also have a load balancer there
which handles all the internal traffic
between the microservices.
It is bad practice
to use your external load balancer
for internal traffic,
because now you're exposing
your internal traffic to the outside,
right.
It's better to keep that all internal
inside that micro segmented section there.
So keep keep that in mind.
Normally
if you're inside that micro segmented
network we call that East-West traffic.
Between your microservices
north South would be that public exposed.
I'm reaching outside of my, my network.
I'm reaching outside my little cluster
that I've established.
That's that's how the terminology is used.
Okay, so we talked about external.
Remember, external
is clients from the outside
being routed to,
the message is being routed
to internal microservices.
Internal.
It's balancing traffic
across the private network
in between the microservices themselves.
We also have regional and global.
We talked a little bit about this,
load balancers that handle regional
can handle, multiple regions
or where I'm distributing,
my workload across multiple regions
and even globally.
Right. I've seen some global,
load balancers that do proximity
requests for data stores.
There's some companies out there
that do this wonderfully
well so that if I'm downloading something,
a movie, let's say,
or maybe this lecture from YouTube.
YouTube does a wonderful job at this.
Where are you from?
Where are you getting it from?
Where's the lowest latency?
Most geographically geographic
proximal location that I can connect you
to to decrease, the latency
and the amount of, network hops
maybe that I need to make.
So these read these global load balancers,
for, routing, work very, very well.
And there's lots of
examples out there for that.
Okay.
Health checks.
This is a really important aspect,
for these load balancers.
They need to be able to find out
what's going on
with microservices
that, have registered with it.
So they typically
you register your health, check.
Endpoint
so that these load balancers can say,
all right,
I've got something going on here.
I got a request coming
in, the health check
that has been running periodically.
Is it giving me back good information?
If the answer is yes, I got it back.
Good information.
It stays in the queue
as soon as I get unhealthy timeouts.
Then I remove it from the the load
balancing queue
and I decide what I'm going to do.
There's lots of options
whether I say, hey,
let's start up a new instance
and tear this one down.
If it's not doing anything,
things like that.
So those are options that you can
establish and a lot of the load balancers.
But the idea here
is that that health checker,
pools
periodically and runs that health check.
Now, some architectures
have gone away with that.
And they have said, well,
instead of pooling,
I'm just going to be event driven.
So when a back end goes down,
I'm sitting on a socket
that says, hey, that back end
just went down and I'm notified.
That is another option.
You decrease
the amount of network traffic, by,
watching for drop sockets.
But if you miss that drop socket
event, you have no idea
that the back end went down.
And that has happened
in some of the big cloud service
providers where they've had massive
cascading failures
because of the architectural elements
that they put into place.
So be careful that make sure that you have
maybe a dual mechanism
in there that your health checks
health checker is running periodically.
Most of the load balancers
do a pretty good job with this. Now.
Okay.
Remember
health checks are probing the back
end on a TCP IP port.
Send you message.
Give me something back.
I can access you. I get it back.
Configurable settings.
As I mentioned before, what are the
healthy and unhealthy thresholds?
If I ping you,
and, or I do a health
check on you and you respond
in a certain amount of time,
I put a threshold on that or what
percentage
of health check,
failures in my willing to accept before
I take you out of the rotation.
Okay.
So it's highly configurable on the health
checks.
Now, once
I know that I've got my microservices
running and I can access them,
how do I determine where
I'm going to redirect traffic coming from?
The client
or even on an internal load balancer
from anyone that's making a request?
How do I determine that?
Well, there's lots of different options.
The easiest, believe it or not.
And probably the most, used is round
robin, where I'm just
I just go through the list
you get at this time, the next one gets it
the next time and just run to the list.
Equal distribution
in sequence, highly predictable.
Turns out it's pretty effective.
Pretty effective for most workloads.
Other workloads where you've got,
there are workloads where I've got highly,
variable, runtimes on requests.
This may not work as well,
because if I've got,
high variability
where some are only taking
milliseconds
and others are taking minutes,
I could easily, create bottlenecks
in other microservices and running.
All right,
where I. Oh, now I'm waiting for that one.
It's really busy,
but it's it's turned to do it.
So other options
and schedulers have come up.
Least connections latency biased
or proximity.
Weighted higher
and they can look at CPU time network.
There's lots of different options and then
do some some schedules are very complex
and look at certain, service
level agreements
or quality of service,
that you're looking for.
You have to understand,
what the different options are
and make sure that you're using the right,
traffic distribution algorithm.
And which ones are available
on the load balancer that you've chosen.
All right.
Let's talk about security
a little bit. Right.
So I've got, TLS and I've also got, SSL.
Termination now at the application,
layer seven,
when I get that connection, come in,
I terminate the TLS at that connection,
and I can reestablish a new cert
to the back end.
Right.
I re encrypt it and send it back in
this makes sure
that the client is not sharing keys
with the back end microservice.
It's actually sharing the keys
with the load balancer.
And then the load balancer sharing keys
with the, microservice on the back end.
That seems to be the most secure way
to do things if you want super secure
in your load balancer,
because there is a time when, the,
messages are decrypted
and then re encrypted
in the load balancer.
And that could be a, a point of,
contention
for some, highly secure things.
It can't have anything.
You know, I don't want the load balancer
seeing the the text there,
the clear text, you can actually run
a load balancer in Secure Enclave
or Confidential computing across
Secure Enclave, where
everything still,
say, stays in encrypted memory.
Really cool technology out there
that you could, take a look at,
but understand that I am decrypting
in the load balancer and recreating,
re encrypting A before goes to the back
end pool
where it's sharing keys back and forth.
So it does.
There is some benefit in that.
I'm offloading certificate management
into the load balancer.
So there's one place where I'm doing
all that certificate management.
So the my the microservices
don't need to know about it.
And the clients can interact
with the load balancer.
So keep that in mind.
Okay.
Some advanced features
I can do content based routing
because I can look at the message
possibly if it's not completely decrypted,
when I,
decrypt it in the load balancer,
I can look at the types of messages
I'm sending, and I can reroute it
based off of the headers of path,
or even the messages themselves,
to the appropriate back end.
I can also gracefully remove
back ends during updates so I can
I can easily update things
in a running system.
I can have sticky sessions, with the load
balancer across multiple microservices.
Even if a microservice goes down,
and it's replica, I can pick it up
and I can have that sticky session
across the different,
replicas of a microservice.
I can, create my web application
firewall directly
in, into the load balancer as well.
And of course, the auto scaling,
which we've already talked a lot about.
All right.
That's practices.
First off use health checks,
to test for fast failure detection.
Separate internal and external load
balancer roles.
They are different.
It's higher secure that way.
Implement SSL at the edge for security.
Use global load balancers for multi-region
failover.
Organizations have got caught with this.
When a region goes down in the cloud
and all of a sudden they're completely
hosed and they can't work anymore.
If you had a global load balancer,
you could do multi-region failover.
So you could easily flip it over
and you'd be in good shape.
Make sure that you are leveraging
the auto scale algorithms
that are already built
in to these systems.
And we'll talk about, some of this
with, Kubernetes and its integration
with, these load balancers and then,
you know, use, restricted modifications
on anything that you're doing
with secure, load balancer,
especially the API.
If it's really cool,
if you've got security, a security API
for your load balancer,
but you don't do any of the authentication
because now anyone can now
do whatever they want
with your load balancer,
and they'll take over
your whole application.
All your network traffic.
So be mindful that also make sure you're
monitoring your load balancing metrics.
There's
a lot of really good metrics in there.
That will give you an idea
of what's going on in your application.
All right.
Remember load balancing
gives me resilience scalability, security.
Make sure you understand
the difference between L4 and L7.
Run those health checks.
Take a look at the different
routing algorithms that you want to use,
and make sure that you're building
in your autoscaling into the load
balancer as well.
So the load balancer knows that, hey,
I've automatically scaled
up, more instances.
And it also needs to know
when to scale up more instances.
So it's it's a nice,
integration between the two.